RG 040, Post-War Planning Board
Connecticut State Library
Post-War Planning Board records
1943-1945
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Post-War Planning Board
5 cubic feet
The Post-War Planning Board, authorized by an Act of the General Assembly of June 2, 1943, was established to study problems of post-war readjustment and reconversion in the state and formulate plans to deal with them.
RG040
T002693
Historical Note
Authorized by an act of the General Assembly in June 1943, the Post–War Planning Board’s charge was “to study and formulate plans for the readjustment and reconversion of agriculture, manufacturing, business and mercantile activities within the state from a wartime to a peacetime basis.” An appointed Board of fourteen, headed by President Charles Seymour of Yale, was supplemented by committees of business and community leaders in various fields and by a small executive and research staff headed by Herbert L. Crapo. The Board met twenty times from September 22, 1943 to June 19, 1945. It completed an Interim Report to the Governor in October 1944 and a Final Report was published in 1946, both under the title Post-War Connecticut. The Board legally ceased to exist on July 1, 1945.
Scope and Content
The record group consists of minutes of meetings, September 22, 1943-June 19, 1945; correspondence, working papers and drafts of reports; newspaper clippings and other reference materials; photographs; completed confidential employment and planning surveys; and subcommittee records.
Related Material
RG 005:029, Office of the Governor, Raymond E. Baldwin, 1943-1945, files headed "Post-War Planning Board".
RG 049, Records of the Veternans Advisory Commission, 1943-1949.
RG 050 Records of the War Council, 1940-1945.
The Board's "Research Data" files (described in document M-144; see Item 1) were evidently kept by the Development Commission.
The State Library has in its collections copies of the Board's interim report, a printed summary titled Quick Facts, its final report and some research studies.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. Post-War Planning Board
Subjects:
City planning -- Connecticut; Connecticut. Post-War Planning Board -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut -- Evonomic policy -- 1945-1960; Industries -- Connecticut; Public works -- Connecticut; Regional planning -- Connecticut; Reconstruction (1939-1951) -- Connecticut; Unemployed -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Clippings; Correspondence; Minutes; Photograhs; Reports
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
The Board legally ceased to exist on July 1, 1945, and its files apparently went to the Development Commission, which turned some of them over to the State Library in August 1945.
Container List
- Records, 1943-1945
  - 1. "Records", 1943 June 2-1945 June 30 (Box 1)
    Contains mimeographed records of the Board, including minutes of some meetings, reports to the Board by staff officers and committees, the Act creating the Board (M-1), its Interim Report (printed; M-115), and a report on its records (M-144). Minutes of Board meetings are in Item 2.
    Arranged numerically (M-1 to M-144) and approximately chronologically in two binders (M-115 separate). A numerical list is in the first binder.
  - 2. Minutes of meetings, 1943 September 22-1945 June 19 (Box 1)
    Contains mimeographed copies of minutes of meetings of the Board.
    Chronological.
  - 3. Correspondence, 1943-1945
    Alphabetical by correspondent or, in a few cases, by subject (e.g. employment, Housatonic Valley Parkway, statistical index (under "index"), mailing list, office staff, etc.).
    - A-F (Box 2)
    - G-M (Box 3)
    - N-Z (Box 4)
  - 4. General file, 1943-1945
    Contains correspondence, working papers, minutes, reference materials and other papers pertaining to the work of the Board and the preparation of its recommendations.
    - Meetings (Box 5)
    - Minutes (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Personnel (Box 5)
    - Releases (and clippings) (Box 5)
    - Reports of the Directors to the Board (Box 5)
    - Seymour, Charles (Box 6)
    - Waugh, Albert E. (Box 6)
    - Committees (General) (Box 6)
      - Drafting (Box 6)
      - Legislative (Box 6)
      - Liaison (Box 6)
      - Personnel (Box 6)
      - Policy and Programs (Box 6)
      - Public Information (Box 6)
    - Committees (Substantive) (Box 6)
      - Community Development and Housing (Box 6)
      - Education (Box 6)
      - Finance (Box 6-7)
      - Industry and Labor (Box 7)
      - Medical Care and Health (Box 7)
      - Public Utilities and Transportation (Box 8)
      - Public Works (Box 8-9)
      - Recreation (Box 9)
      - Rural Life and Agriculture (Box 9)
  - 5. Employment and planning survey reports, 1944 (Box 10)
    Contains form questionnaire replies from companies concerning estimates of employees required and construction and development plans for the immediate post-war period. Most are marked "NG" (no good?).
    Unarranged.
  - 6. Personal history statements of Board and Committee members, 1944 (Box 10)
    Contains form statements of education and business and public experience. There are some photographs.
  - 7. Miscellaneous (Box 10)
    Includes correspondence with State departments on administrative and other matters, and reference materials on post-war planning.